Donald Barthelme, Sr. Architectural Papers, 1924-1997
University of Houston Libraries
Donald Barthelme, Sr. Architectural Papers
1924-1997
Barthelme, Donald Sr. (1907-1996)
2001-003
50 boxes; 1,883 drawings; 9,007 photographic images; 30 linear feet of archival material
Donald Barthelme, Sr. was a prominent Houston architect and professor at the University of Houston and Rice University. The collection contains his architectural drawings, papers, photographs, and other materials.
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Donald Barthelme, Sr. was a prominent Houston architect and professor at the University of Houston and Rice University. He was the first Houston architect to attain international recognition, and during the 1950s was one of the city’s best known architects. His career was notable because he combined a distinguished architectural practice with an intense commitment to architectural education.
Barthelme was born in Galveston, Texas on August 4, 1907. He attended the Rice Institute in Houston for two years before transferring in 1926 to the University of Pennsylvania, where he studied under the French master Paul Philippe Cret. He graduated in 1930, winning the Arthur Spayd Brook Bronze Medal for Design. After graduation he worked first in Cret’s office and then in the Philadelphia firm of Zantzinger, Borie, and Medary.
The Great Depression forced Barthelme to return to Texas late in 1932. He practiced on his own in Galveston for several years, surviving on small commissions. In 1935 he moved to Houston to work for noted architect John F. Staub, but stayed only a few months before being called to Dallas to work on the Texas Centennial Exposition. There he was the lead designer of the Hall of State, the centerpiece of the exposition and today considered a masterpiece of the Art Deco style. In 1937 he returned to Staub’s office in Houston, where he remained for two years before leaving to open his own practice. In the early 1940s he did war-related work, first as a designer on the Avion Village Housing Project near Dallas, and later as supervising architect for the Big Spring Air Base in West Texas and defense housing projects in Galveston and Sweeny, Texas.
Barthelme’s career began in earnest in 1942, with the first of many projects for the West Columbia Independent School District in Brazoria County, Texas. Over the next two decades his school designs earned national and international awards and appeared in numerous publications. His best known project, and arguably his best work, was the West Columbia Elementary School (1951). He designed other elementary schools in West Columbia and Sweeny, Texas; additions to the high schools in West Columbia and Sweeny; and finally, the West Columbia Senior High School (1963). During the 1950s he was acknowledged as an expert on the design of schools, and wrote and lectured extensively on the subject. This led to his election in 1955 as a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects, an honor accorded architects who make a significant contribution to the advancement of architecture.
Although he retired from active practice in 1963, he continued to participate in competitions and in 1964 was one of seven finalists in the competition to design the headquarters building for the American Institute of Architects in Washington, D.C. His other works include the Barthelme Residence (1941), St. Rose of Lima Church and School (1948), the Adams Petroleum Center (1957), and Highland Heights Elementary School (1959) in Houston. St. Rose of Lima was the first modernist Catholic church in Houston, and was the first Houston building to win an award of merit from the A.I.A.
Barthelme began his other major professional endeavor in 1946, when he joined the faculty of the Architecture Department at the University of Houston. He helped shape the program in its early years and was an influential member of the faculty until his retirement in 1973. He also served as William Ward Watkin Professor and chairman of the Architecture Department at Rice University from 1959 to 1961. He is remembered at both institutions for his rigorous standards and for his efforts to redesign the curriculum to integrate all parts of the architectural education process. He also was a visiting professor at the University of Pennsylvania and Tulane University.
In retirement Barthelme turned to writing, as he recorded ideas developed over a lifetime of practice and teaching. In the late 1970s he began writing a book promoting his philosophy that architects should be more concerned with the user’s experience of architecture than with its purely formal aspects. Together with his voluminous lecture notes, the partial manuscript and related materials in the collection form a body of writing that captures the humanist values he tried to instill in his students.
Barthelme married Helen Bechtold (1907–1995) of Philadelphia on June 21, 1930. From 1931 to 1947 the couple had five children: Donald, Joan, Peter, Frederick, and Steven. Donald (1931–1989) achieved fame as a writer and novelist and from 1980 to 1989 was a professor at the University of Houston, where he helped establish the reputation of the University’s acclaimed Creative Writing Program. The Donald Barthelme Literary Papers are housed in a separate collection in the University of Houston Libraries’ Department of Special Collections. Also accomplished writers, Frederick and Steven Barthelme teach Creative Writing at the University of Southern Mississippi on the faculty of the university’s Center for Writers. Peter has also published several novels, while Joan served for many years as an executive with a large Houston oil company.
Donald Barthelme, Sr. died on July 16, 1996.
Sources:
Stephen Fox, Donald Barthelme, 1907-1996, Cite 35 (Fall 1996): 8-11.
Yolita Schmidt, Donald Barthelme, Texas Architect (Nov.-Dec. 1989): 44.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Barthelme, Sr. Architectural Papers cover the period 1924 to 1997 and are comprised of his architectural drawings; business and personal files; memorabilia; photographic prints, negatives, and slides; as well as lecture notes and other materials from his teaching career. The collection occupies 35 linear feet and 15 drawers of flat files, and is stored in 43 boxes and 92 oversize folders.
Barthelme’s architectural drawings document his professional practice, from his earliest commissions in Galveston in 1933, to his last, in Houston, in 1964. Of the 1,883 sheets of original drawings, the majority are (a) studies and preliminary drawings and (b) working drawings. Few presentation drawings survive, but many have been preserved in photographs. Of particular interest are the materials for his two largest projects, the Adams Petroleum Center and West Columbia Senior High School, because of the large number of colored-pencil renderings, which he did to study different design ideas. Missing are projects that he may have done in other offices, such as his Philadelphia, Dallas, Staub, and defense work. With the exception of materials for a few early projects, for the Adams Petroleum Center, and for the Kellaway house, most of Barthelme’s business correspondence and project files are believed to have been destroyed when he closed his office in 1963.
Barthelme is remembered as a teacher and a philosopher. He left extensive lecture notes for his courses at the University of Houston and memoranda that outlined his new curriculum for the Architecture Department at Rice University. His lecture notes illustrate his ideas, but the best organized statement of his philosophy of architecture is found in his writings. Of special interest are his manuscript for a book, a handwritten critique of the manuscript by an unknown reviewer (probably his son, Frederick), and an attempt to articulate his ideas on architecture in a lengthy 1975 letter to John McGinty, then head of the Houston Chapter of the A.I.A.
Other writings show the breadth of Barthelme’s interest in education. In October 1959 he appeared at a conference at the University of Michigan in which prominent architects discussed Dr. Lloyd Trump’s study for educational reform, funded by the Ford Foundation. Barthelme presented his own proposals for a new secondary school curriculum and a schematic design for a high school. The conference proceedings were published the next year. Barthelme also prepared 359 slides in connection with this presentation, which are part of his photographic materials.
As an enthusiastic amateur photographer, Barthelme took thousands of pictures and often did his own processing in a home darkroom. This large photographic collection documents his architectural practice and his travels in Mexico. It is comprised of 1,309 black-and-white prints¬¬ (most 8 x 10 and larger); 999 4 x 5 black-and-white negatives; 67 35mm black-and-white negatives; 840 2 ¼ x 3 ¼ black-and-white negatives; 49 2 ¼ x 3 ¼ color glass-mount transparencies; and 2,856 35mm color slides. In many cases a print has a corresponding negative, but these materials are not cross-referenced. Many pictures of Barthelme’s buildings are known to be the work of Dallas photographer Ulric Meisel, but unless noted otherwise, Barthelme is presumed to be the photographer on the items in this series.
Among the photographic materials is a bound scrapbook of photographic prints and clippings of Barthelme’s architectural projects. It also includes important awards, certificates, and licenses, although some that had become loose were removed to a separate folder. The scrapbook comprises 120 prints (mounted and unmounted) and 72 leaves, or 116 total items.
When the Department of Special Collections processed Barthelme’s papers, his heirs allowed the department to create digital files of a portion of their large collection of family photographs, which were retained by the heirs. This collection, covering the period 1930 to 1986, includes pictures of Barthelme, his wife, and his children, mostly in and around the family home in Houston. Approximately 150 sheets of photographic negatives are preserved in 2,887 digital images on CD-ROM, with record prints in a binder. This is intended only as a study collection for scholars. The images are owned by the Barthelme estate and may not be copied or reproduced without its written permission.
Barthelme’s professional career is further recorded in his extensive file of newspaper and magazine clippings. Personal materials include biographical information, student work, interviews, and correspondence, as well as artifacts and memorabilia.
Acquisition Information
The Donald Barthelme, Sr. Architectural Papers were donated to the University of Houston Libraries by Frederick and Steven Barthelme in 2001.
Access Restrictions
Open for Research.
Related material
Barthelme’s personal library of 59 books was separated from the Donald Barthelme, Sr. Architectural Papers and transferred to the University’s William R. Jenkins Architecture & Art Library, where they were integrated into its Closed Collections and Special Collections. Barthelme earlier donated most of his books to the University’s Architecture Library in 1977 (the name of the library changed in 1986). An inventory of his personal library appears at the end of this finding aid. Call numbers for these titles may be found in the University of Houston Libraries’online catalog at http://library.uh.edu.
Detailed Description
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers includes records generally created outside of Barthelme's professional life, such as biographical information, student work, interview transcripts, and correspondence. This series contains 28 folders arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Engraving, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter, Tau Sigma Delta, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate, Tau Sigma Delta, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wedding Invitation, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Woodcut, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Program, Commencement Ceremonies, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Telegram (Birth), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Christmas Card, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Announcement, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Identification Card, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Identification Card, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Telegram (Award), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper manuscript (Donald Jr.), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Awards, 1945-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cartoon, Houston Post, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Curriculum Vitae, Pt. 1, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Curriculum Vitae, Pt. 2, 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - University of Houston, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Application for Research Support, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Inventories of Drawings and Photographs, 1973, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence, Pt. 1, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal Correspondence, Pt. 2, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal Correspondence, Pt. 3, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dallas Historical Society, Pt. 1, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dallas Historical Society, Pt. 2, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cite Interview with DB, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Camera Repair, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Columbia-Brazoria I.S.D., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings and Speeches
  The Writings and Speeches Series contains files related to Barthelme’s writings in draft or typescript form, and talks to student and professional groups. The latter includes materials related to an important conference on educational reform at the University of Michigan in which Barthelme was one of the principal speakers. (See Scope and Contents Note for details.)
  - Writings: The Four-Classroom System, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Writings: A School Planning Approach, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Writings: Top Lighting is Here to Stay, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Writings: A Plan of Organization for a Secondary School Curriculum, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Writings: Rice TV Program, ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Writings: A New Curriculum, J.A.E., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Writings: Growit Yourself College, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Writings: Le Roi Est Mort, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Writings: Architectural Education 1990, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Writings: Draft article- City Planning, ca. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Writings: Masters - Notebook Series, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Writings: McGinty File, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Writings: Writing - 1977, Pts. 1-4, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41-44)
  - Writings: Typescript, Pts. 1-3, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 45-47)
  - Talks: A.I.A., N.E. Texas Chapter, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Talks: Secondary School Curriculum, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Talks: A.I.A., Mississippi Chapter (incl. notecards), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Talks: U of H: Opening Talk, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Talks: Time and Man, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Talks: Texas A&M: Materials and Messages, Pts.1-3, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 53-55)
  - Talks: Miscellaneous, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Talks: Thesis Program, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Michigan Conference: Draft Speech (Master) 1959 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Michigan Conference: Text of Speech, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Michigan Conference: Graphics for Speech, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Michigan Conference: Architectural Forum article, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Michigan Conference: E.F.L. Booklet, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Newspaper Clippings
  Barthelme kept an extensive file of newspaper clippings about his career. These are stored in five folders arranged in chronological order, followed by two folders with oversize clippings, also in chronological order.
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 1, 1936-1950 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 2, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 3, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 4, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 5, 1958-1964, 1981, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 6, 1948-1957(oversize) (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Clippings, Newspapers, Pt. 7, 1958-1960(oversize) (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Reprints
  This series contains reprints of magazine and journal articles written by or about Barthelme.
  - Photostat, newspaper article, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Magazine, Texas Architect, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Article, Schools, Architectural Forum, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Article, Better School Competition, The School Executive, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Article, The Schools of Donald Barthelme, The School Executive, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Article, The Record Reports, Architectural Record, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - TRA Journal, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Article, The Four Classroom Unit, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Article, The Record Reports, Architectural Record, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Magazine, School Plant Studies, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Article, Top Lighting is Here to Stay, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Bulletin of the National Institute for Architectural Education, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Article, Three Ace Schools for the Trump Plan, Architectural Forum, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Article, Growit Yourself, Progressive Architecture, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Brochures, Catalogs and Programs
  Barthelme saved brochures, exhibition catalogs, and conference programs of special interest.
  - Prospectus, UH Architecture program, ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Exhibition Catalog (Dallas), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Conference Program (Dallas), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Conference Program (Houston), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Conference Program (San Antonio), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Festival Program, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Exhibition Catalog (Houston), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Lecture Program, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Conference Program (Chicago), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Brochure, Adams Petroleum Center (small), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Brochure, Adams Petroleum Center (large), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Program, Style Show, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Exhibition Catalog (USIA- Germany), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Exhibition Catalog (Houston) Ten Years of Houston Architecture,1959 (Box 1, Folder 97)
- Reference Articles
  This series contains magazine articles that Barthelme saved for reference.
  - Article, Population Explosion, Sierra Club Bulletin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Article, The Nonsense Explosion, New Republic, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Article, Storyville, New Yorker (about Donald Jr.), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Miscellaneous- Interior Design Studies, Pts. 1-4, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 101-104)
- Memorabilia
  Memorabilia include Barthelme’s personal drafting equipment and other effects, contained in Boxes 2 and 3. Professional awards and a scrapbook of the high school newspaper he edited (now in very fragile condition) are contained in oversize flat box 4.
  - Barthelme’s personal drafting equipment 1992 (Box 2)
  - Barthelme’s personal drafting equipment 1992 (Box 3)
  - Diploma: UH Professor Emeritus, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Certificates and awards, 1942-1957 (Box 4)
  - Art Prints, Italy, undated (Box 4)
  - Parking Facilities Study, APC Bldg., 1957 (Box 4)
  - Plaque: The School Executive Better School Design Competition, Award for West Columbia Elementary, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, Purple Quill, Ball H.S., Galveston, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Sketch, Donald Barthelme, Jr. playing drums, by Pat Goeters, ca. late 1940's (Box 4)
- Magazine and Journals
  This series contains complete issues of magazines and journals that Barthelme saved because they pertained to his career or contained matters of special interest. The issues are in chronological order and are contained in three oversize flat boxes.
  - Fortune Oversize clipping, September 1954 (Box 5)
  - Life Oversize reprint, June 1957 (Box 5)
  - Christopher Alexander paper, October 1966 (Box 5)
  - 10 Designs: Community Colleges, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Bulletin of the A.I.A., May-June 1956 (Box 5)
  - The School Executive, June 1953 (Box 5)
  - Time, September 1953 (Box 5)
  - Architectural Forum, October 1952 (Box 5)
  - Life, June 1957 (Box 5)
  - Artek furniture catalog, 1975 (Box 6)
  - A.I.A. Journal, November 1975 (Box 6)
  - Texas Parade, July 1975 (Box 6)
  - The Center Magazine, July/Aug. 1975 (Box 6)
  - The Center Magazine, March/April 1973 (Box 6)
  - The Center Magazine, Jan./Feb. 1973 (Box 6)
  - Journal of Architectural Education, 1971 (Box 6)
  - The New Yorker, September 26, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Interchange, Fall 1997 (Box 7)
  - Texas Architect, Nov.-Dec. 1989 (Box 7)
  - Texas Architect, March-April 1988 (Box 7)
  - Texas Architect, May-June 1986 (Box 7)
  - Progressive Architecture, August 1986 (Box 7)
- Teaching: University of Houston
  Barthelme served as an architecture professor at the University of Houston from 1946 to 1958 and from 1963 to 1973. This series contains his lecture notes, studio problems, and other resource materials from this period of his career arranged in subseries by topic, including the following: (1) Barthelme’s notecards for talks and class lectures, contained in a small box, with each talk separated by a divider; (2) Gradebooks, school curricula, course descriptions, and other organizational material, arranged in rough chronological order; (3) Articles and other reference materials Barthelme quoted or used in his lectures, arranged chronologically within each of his subject headings, using his titles, and for the most part following his order; and (4) Barthelme’s class and lecture notes, arranged chronologically within each of his subject headings, using his titles, and for the most part following his order.
  - Notecards
  - notecards for talks, class lectures, undated (Box 8)
  - Organizational Material (Box 9)
    - Gradebooks, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum Proposal, UH, Pts. 1-2, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - Description Proposed Curriculum, Pts. 1-3, undated (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
    - Outline Proposed Curriculum, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Course Descriptions, 1967-1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Human Studies Program, 1969-1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Concepts, Scope of Course, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Concepts, Research Programs, 1967, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Concepts, Organizational Notes, Pts. 1-6, 1966-1972 (Box 9, Folder 12-17)
    - First Year Program, Pts. 1-4, 1970-1972 (Box 9, Folder 18-21)
    - First Year Program, Pts. 1-2, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 22-23)
    - First Year Program, 1963-64, Dean’s Copy (sent 1968), Pts. 1-3, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 24-26)
    - Worksheets, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Reference Files (Box 9)
    - Reference Files: Theory, Pts. 1-6, 1948-1969 (Box 9, Folder 28-33)
    - Reference Files: The City, Pts. 1-9, 1946-1968 (Box 9, Folder 34-42)
    - Reference Files: The City, Pts. 1-6, 1961-1969 (Box 9, Folder 43-48)
    - Reference Files: Space, Pts.1-2, 1965-1969 (Box 9, Folder 49-50)
    - Reference Files: Illustrations, Pts. 1-2, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 51-52)
    - Reference Files: Research, Pts. 1-4, 1958-1970 (Box 9, Folder 53-56)
    - Reference Files: Youth, Pts. 1-3, 1967-1971 (Box 9, Folder 57-59)
    - Reference Files: Architectural Education, Pts. 1-22, 1954-1971 (Box 10, Folder 1-22)
    - Reference Files: Man, Pts. 1-3, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 23-25)
    - Reference Files: Statistics, Pts. 1-3, 1959-1978 (Box 10, Folder 26-28)
    - Reference Files: Articles and Reprints, Pts. 1-7, 1959-1978 (Box 10, Folder 29-35)
    - Reference Files: Miscellaneous, Pts. 1-6, 1959-1969 (Box 10, Folder 36-41)
    - Reference Files: Clippings, Pts. 1-2, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
    - Reference Files: Quotes, Pts. 1-8, 1959-1983 (Box 10, Folder 44-51)
    - Reference Files: Planning Criteria, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Class Notes (Box 11)
    - Introduction to Architecture II - Option, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Exercises, ARC 131, 132, Pts. 1-3, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)